All right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov. Good morning, it is the 18th
day in the עומר, Omer, it is also יום הזיכרון, Yom HaZikaron,
so our learning should be in memory of all those who have
given their lives to protect the people and the State of Israel.
We pick up today's דף Daf is ס"א, Samech Aleph, 61, we
pick up towards the bottom of ס"ה עמוד ב', Samech Hey Amud
Bet, a little bit before the משנה. Mishnah. We were dealing with
somebody who says, "this is your גט get from now and after
30 days." There we said there was a whole range of possibilities,
whether it meant from now, whether it meant it was a question
whether you mean from now or 30 days, or whether it was
some ongoing type of a way in which the גט get took
place, the גט, get, I said גט, get, I meant קידושין, Kiddushin,
we're comparing it to גט, get, but anyway an ongoing way in
which the קידושין Kiddushin took place. And then the most recent משנה,
Mishnah, which is, "this is your קידושין, Kiddushin, I am marrying you,"
let me try that again, "on the condition that על מנת ש
Al Menat She you give me, I give you 200 זוז," zuz,
and there, although there was some debate, overwhelmingly all the evidence is
that על מנת Al Menat means כמעכשיו דמי. Ke'mei Achshav Damei. I
am marrying you now on the condition that at some time in
the future this condition is met. כל האומר על מנת כאומר מעכשיו
דמי. Kol Ha'omer Al Menat Ke'omer Me'achshav Damei. That was clearly a
position of רבי, Rebbe, there was nobody obviously who argued on רבי,
Rebbe, many thought that that's a wide assumption that that's a consensus
position, although there is a minority voice that that actually is a
matter of debate. Okay, we pick up at the bottom of ס'
עמוד ב', Samech Amud Bet,
right before, two lines before the lines get at the bottom of
the narrow lines, על מנת שאתן לך מכאן ועד שלושים יום. Al
Menat She'etayn Lecha Mi'kan V'ad Shloshim Yom. "If this is your, I'm
marrying you if I give you 200 זוז zuz from now to
30 days," he has to give it within 30 days, otherwise it
doesn't work. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously that's exactly what he said. No, מהו
דתימא, mah d'teima, I might have thought לאו תנאה הוה הוא, lav
tna hava hu,
when he says within 30 days, it's not part of the condition,
וזרוזי קאמר, uzruzei ka'amar, he's just saying the condition is I'll give
you 200 זוז, zuz, within 30 days is like a promise of
what he's doing to
sort of urge himself, encourage himself to do it quickly, but it's
not actually strictly part of the condition. קא משמע לן Kamashmalan that
we don't say that, that he framed it as part of the
condition, so if that's not done within 30 days, she's not מקודשת.
mekudeshet. על מנת שיש לי מאתיים זוז, Al Menat She'yesh Li Matayim
Zuz, if I have 200 זוז, zuz, she's married if he does
have 200 זוז. zuz. וניחו שמא יש לו, Unaychu shema yesh lo,
so the simple sense of the משנה Mishnah is she's married if
he has, the implication being that if he doesn't have 200 זוז,
zuz, she's definitely not married. But how do you prove a negative?
How do you prove that he doesn't have 200 זוז? zuz? So
you check his bank account. So what did you do? You looked
in his wallet. How do you know, maybe he's got it hidden
in some offshore account? How can you assert obviously definitively that she's
not married?
ועוד תניא, V'od Tanya, cute, and we also taught חיישינן שמא יש
לו. chashinan shema yesh lo. We have a ברייתא Braita that says
explicitly that even if you can't bring, if it doesn't seem that
he has 200 זוז, zuz, she's not definitely not married, we're concerned
that he might have 200 זוז. zuz. So the גמרא Gemara says
לא קשיא, lo kashya, you're right, הא בקידושי ודאי הא בקידושי ספק.
ha bekiddushei vada'i ha bekiddushei safek. It's
interesting when it says הא ha be-this and הא ha be-that, it's
like an אוקימתא. ukimta. But this isn't an אוקימתא. ukimta. This is
basically saying they're all talking about the same thing. Our משנה Mishnah
means that if he doesn't have 200 זוז, zuz, she's not definitely
married. The ברייתא Braita clarifies that she's not definitely married, but she's
also not definitely not married. That since you can't prove if a
תנאי tnai has been satisfied, the result is ספק safek married, which
is of course the worst of both worlds. She wants to marry
another man, she needs a גט, get, but she's not definitively married
to this man. Okay, so you're right, when you cannot prove if
a תנאי tnai has been satisfied, then the result is ספק. safek.
על מנת שאראך מאתיים זוז, Al Menat She'arech Matayim Zuz, "I'm going
to give you, I show you 200 זוז." zuz. If he shows
her, she's married. But he has, the משנה Mishnah clarifies, she has
to show, he has to show her of his own money. He
can't show her some money on like, if he's a money changer
and it's other people's money, that's not sufficient. The example I gave
was like let's say he says on the condition that I will
show you a house filled with jewelry, he can't go ahead and
take her to the house filled with impressionist paintings, he can't go
and take her to the Metropolitan. Okay, the implication is that it's
his. All right, so the גמרא Gemara says תנא לא נתכוון אלא
להראות משלו, Tana, lo niskaven ela l'rot mishelo, when he says show
you, it means I'll show you my own, you know, that's clear
from the implications. I'll show you that I have it, even though
he didn't say the words that I have it. And that's interesting,
right? Because there's a case where technically the words were satisfied, but
we say, you know, sometimes you use context, it's not דברים שבלב,
devarim shebalev, because if there's an implicit context that everybody understands, then
that defines it. ואם הראה על השולחן אינה מקודשת, V'im her'ah al
hashulchan einah mekudeshet, and if he just showed her on a table
that he was like a money changer and it wasn't his money,
then she's not מקודשת. mekudeshet. פשיטא, Peshita, obviously. No, לא צריכא דאף
על גב דנקיט דמי בעיסקא, lo tzricha d'af al gav d'nakat damei
b'iska, let's say it is money, other people's money that he is
investing. Okay, so that's like somewhat of a middle thing. It's not
completely not his money, he's been given the money to invest, he
has maybe a stake in the money, so he's got... I've got
a billion dollars of assets that I invest
in my mutual fund here, but nevertheless it's not your billion dollars.
So even though you're going to make profit off of it, okay,
it's not your money so that is not a satisfying of the
condition. Yes.
So if someone goes for a minute back to the very first
case, על מנת שאתן לך מכאן ועד שלשים יום al menat she'eten
lach mikan v'ad shloshim yom פשיטא pshita מהו דתימא mahu detema רבנן.
Rabbanan. Right. How can על מנת al menat possibly not be a
תנאי? tnai?
No, על מנת שאתן לך al menat she'eten lach is definitely a
תנאי, tnai, but מכאן ועד שלשים יום mikan v'ad shloshim yom might
be more not a directly part of the תנאי tnai itself.
So the concern in the גמרא Gemara is that the על מנת
al menat language is now counterbalanced with language that might not be
a תנאי. tnai.
How much of the statement is strictly part of the condition? I'll
give you I'll give you a hundred dollars, and let's even make
it more complicated. Let's say he takes a pause.
I am מקדש mekadesh you on the condition I give you a
hundred dollars, pause, within thirty days. Okay? So how much would you
say that that's like an additional thing like I'm promising to try
to do it within thirty days or is that a strictly a
part of the condition? So the גמרא Gemara does say it's not
a big ספק, safek, but the גמרא Gemara just clarifies that you
read the second half of that statement remains part of a strictly
part of the condition. Okay. Yes.
The last case, is it fundamentally because an investment is not your
money anymore or is it because of the lack of liquidity back
in?
No, it's not that it's not your money anymore, it never was
your money. People gave him their money for him to invest and
he gets a percentage.
Oh, it's the other way around.
Yeah, yeah, so therefore he's showing her two hundred זוז zuz and
two hundred זוז zuz that he even has certain rights to and
will get certain profit out of, but it's not his two hundred
זוז. zuz. It's two hundred זוז zuz he was given to invest.
Okay. Okay.
Now, so the גמרא Gemara says like this: על מנת, al menat,
the next משנה Mishnah is almost the same except with a different
sort of case scenarios. על מנת שיש לי בית כור עפר, al
menat sheyesh li beit kor afar, on the condition that I have
a plot of land the size of a בית כור, beit kor,
which is basically it's five what is
it? It's it's it's רש"י Rashi says seventy-five
thousand. Thank you. Seventy-five thousand square אמה. amah. It's seventy-five thousand square
אמה. amah. Okay. It's an acre, whatever it is. We'll make that
up. I don't know if it's an acre. Okay. Anyway, הרי זו
מקודשת harei zo mekudeshet ויש לו, v'yesh lo, she's married if he
actually has that amount of land. על מנת שיש לי במקום פלוני,
al menat sheyesh li b'makom ploni,
if I have a בית כור beit kor in a certain location,
אם יש לו באותו מקום מקודשת ואם לאו אינה מקודשת. im yesh
lo b'oto makom mekudeshet v'im lav eina mekudeshet. So it's not enough
that he has, he said that it's within a certain location. So
if it's in a different location, she's not married. על מנת שאראך
בית כור עפר, al menat she'arech beit kor afar, if I show
you a בית כור עפר, beit kor afar, הרי זו מקודשת harei
zo mekudeshet
she's married ויראנה v'yarena and he has to show it to her.
But it's going to be clear just like the issue with the
money before, why is he showing it to her if not implicitly
means show you that I have it, not let's just take a
little trip to the country. Okay. ואם הראה בביקא, v'im hera b'vika,
if he shows her in a valley and it's not his and
it's somebody else's or it's ownerless or whatever, אינה מקודשת eina mekudeshet
she's not. Very parallel to the discussion of the money.
What's a בית כור עפר beit kor afar exactly?
You know, about like it's a plot of land. I mean why
it says עפר? afar?
Yeah, I don't know. I mean you're right because the implication here
is as we're going to see in a minute that the point
of showing it to her, well, the point of showing it to
her is to show that he has land to provide for her.
So עפר afar does suggest you're right a little bit more like
it's not fertile land. So I don't know why, yeah, that's the
phrase, בית כור עפר. beit kor afar. I don't know exactly why,
but that's the phrase.
Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says ונחזי שמא יש לו. v'nechezi shema
yesh lo. So again, it sounds from the משנה Mishnah that if
he doesn't have, she's not married, but but why not? She should
be ספק safek married. You can't prove that he doesn't have. ותניא
v'tanya and we say that in a ברייתא, braita, חשינן שמא יש
לו chashinan shema yesh lo that if he doesn't have where she's
still it's a possibility that he does and she's a ספק safek
married. לא קשיא הא בקידושי ודאי והא בקידושי ספק. lo kashya ha
b'kidushei vadai v'ha b'kidushei safek. Like we said before, you're right. The
משנה Mishnah means she's not definitely married if it hasn't been fulfilled.
But if you don't know if he has or not, then I
mean you know, you can't prove a negative, so therefore she's ספק
safek married. So the גמרא Gemara says למה לי למתנא גבי עפרא
ולמה לי למתנא גבי זוזי? lama li l'mitna gabi afra v'lama li
l'mitna gabi zuzei? Why do you have to tell me essentially the
same thing by land and by money? The previous these two משניות.
mishnayot. צריכה tzricha need to tell me both. אי אשמעינן גבי זוזי,
i ashmeinan gabi zuzei, had you said by money, משום דעבידי אינשי
דמטמרי. mishum de'avidi inshi dematmrei. That's because
people hide away their money. They put them in offshore accounts. So
therefore if he didn't if just even if he doesn't have, we
would still say she's ספק מקודשת safek mekudeshet because it's reasonable that
there's money hidden somewhere. אבל ארעא, aval ara, but by land, אימא
אי דאית ליה ארעא קלא אית ליה, eima i d'it lei ara
kala it lei, I might think that if it's not obvious that
he has the land, we should assume that he definitely does not
because it's harder for people to hide away to hide their ownership
of property. It's much easier to just secret money away. So
maybe by the land I would say that if he doesn't have
then
she's ודאי אינה מקודשת. vadai eina mekudeshet. קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that we don't say that. That in either case if he
has she's מקודשת, mekudeshet, if he doesn't have meaning if it doesn't
seem that he has, she's As far as we know he doesn't
have, then we don't say that she's אינה מקודשת, Eina mekudeshet, we
say she's ספק מקודשת. Safek mekudeshet. Okay.
I don't know why women want to get involved with all these
guys, like every single case is like shady.
All right. על מנת שיש לי במקום פלוני אם יש לו. Al
menat she-yesh li b'makom ploni im yesh lo.
Now, how about the other half of the תוספות? Tosafot? What? How
about the other half of the...
why couldn't he just tell me the land without the whatever? That's
a good point, yeah.
Because as I was thinking, like, you could make a case that,
well, my land's somewhere else and you're not somewhere else, like, he
might have inherited from סבא דסבא, Saba d'saba, but that contradicts the
whole basis
for כל נכסי Kol nechasai as the foundation for a whole body
of law.
Right, right, right, exactly.
Right, right, right, right. It's a very good point. Yeah, why couldn't
it have just told me the case by the land and I
would have known the, you know, and if there I'm חיישינן, chaishinan,
then certainly I'm חיישינן chaishinan in the case of the money.
Yeah. Good question. Yeah, I don't know. It's a good question.
Okay. על מנת שיש לי במקום פלוני אם יש לו. Al menat
she-yesh li b'makom ploni im yesh lo. If I have it in
a certain place, then it's only good if the land is in
that place. פשיטא, Pshita, obviously, that's part of the condition. No, מהו
דתימא אימא לה מאי נפקא לך מינה? Mah d'teima eima lah mai
nafka lach mina? Maybe he could say to her, Look, I've got
the land. What, what's the big deal? I said that it was,
you know, 20 miles out of the city and it's 30 miles
out of the city. What, what difference does it make? אנא טרחנא
ומייתינא. Ana arachna u'maitina. The whole issue that I'm promising you the
land, saying that I have the land, is so you know that
we have what to provide, I have what to provide, right? So
it's a little bit further out, it means that it's a little
bit more of a שלעפ schlep to go there to harvest it
and to bring it into the city. Don't worry, I'll do the
שלעפינג. schlepping. It's not a big difference. Okay? קא משמע לן, Ka
mashma lan, tough luck. That's what, that's what's part of the condition
and it doesn't matter as he could say that there's not a
substantive difference. Now, it's an interesting question, right, which is, is it
goes back to this issue about how much, you know, is the,
you know, how, you know, how much do we go strictly by
the words and how much do we apply context? Like we see
by the end when he says, if I show you money, show
you a בית כור, beit kor, going strictly by the words isn't
enough. The context means it has to be his money, it has
to be his plot of land. So how much could we say
also, you know, that's when, in a sense, enough, something wasn't said
and we're sort of filling in something that wasn't said. It's a
little bit different when something was said and we're discounting it, you
know, that I have it in this place or within 30 days
and we say, yeah, you didn't really mean this place, you didn't
really mean 30 days, right? So that's like one question. How much
can we use context to discount something that was said explicitly? That
obviously should be a much higher threshold than to, than to put
something in that wasn't said. You know, the other question is, is
about like, is that it's not like there was a clear implicit
understanding that when I said 30 days, I didn't really mean it.
When I said, you know, when I said this place, you'll say
this place, you don't mean this place. That's not the point. The
point isn't that context makes it clear that you meant something else,
but what you're actually trying to say is that it shouldn't matter,
it shouldn't be a substantive part of the תנאי tnai because nobody
really cares about it and if it's something that you really don't
have a right to care about, then it shouldn't be understood as
part of the condition, right? So that's a different question, like, you
know, what's the קא משמע לן ka mashma lan of the גמרא?
Gemara? Is the קא משמע לן ka mashma lan of the גמרא
Gemara that the woman really does care because she'd rather have land
closer than further away, or is the קא משמע לן ka mashma
lan that even if the woman doesn't care, you don't get to
change it? Let's say he says, you know, I'm, you know, I'm
going to put a, you know, it's over there, it's like 3.7
miles out of the city and it's 3.69 or some other thing
that really we could all agree nobody cares about, right? I mean,
that's maybe not a good example because that's how you define 3.7,
but you know my point, right? You know, if it were something
that actually was trivial, it's the plot of land right by the
red sign and it happened to be the plot of land right
by the blue sign, right? So something we could agree that nobody
cares about. Is that enough to say that that's not part of
the תנאי? tnai? Or do we say, no, you know, nobody questions
what the words meant, you said those words explicitly, there was no
context to say those words meant something else, right? So that's not
clear in the גמרא Gemara what the הוה אמינא hava amina is,
what's the קא משמע לן. ka mashma lan. Is it the קא
משמע לן ka mashma lan that the woman does care or the
קא משמע לן ka mashma lan is it doesn't matter whether she
cares or not? That was part of the condition and it's not
like context says you meant something else, context, even with context, that's
what you meant, so in the end that remains part of the
condition.
And at a certain point, if somebody's constantly not really saying exactly
what's true, right, you get an uneasy feeling about, well, that's also
true.
Yeah, but you're trying to make it like the person cares. I'm
trying to say, like, you know, honest mistake, the person doesn't care,
whatever, so what? It was part of the תנאי, tnai, תנאי tnai
wasn't satisfied, right? What we've seen earlier is that if there were,
if you could add words, like when he says, I'll show it
to you, he meant I'll show you mine, because that's a place
where context and the general understanding that any normal person would have
would be that is what you meant. But when it's clear what
you meant, but it turns out that it was a trivial point
that nobody really should have any right to care about, how much
does that, is, would that be a basis to
say, well, then... על מנת שאראך בית
כור עפר, Al menas she-arecha beis kor afar, תנא: tana: לא נתכוון
אלא להראות לו משלו. lo niskaven ela leharos lo mishelo.
Again, when he says, "show you," it doesn't mean just show you,
it means show you mine. And that's why ואם הראהו בבקעה אינה
מקודשת, v'im herau b'vika einu mekudeshes, if it's in a valley that
he doesn't own, she's not מקודשת. mekudeshes. פשיטא! peshita! לא צריכא דנקט
בדיסטורא, lo tzaricha d'nakeit bidistura, similar to the case before that you're
investing other people's money, here you are a sharecropper of the land.
So nevertheless, even though you're a sharecropper, now that actually is a
good הוה אמינא, hava amina, because you didn't say, "I'll show you
mine." You said, "I'll show you a plot of land," and maybe
I just mean to promise this woman implicitly, show her that I
have what to support our family with, and I actually do have
sharecropping rights into this land, right? So now it's a good הוה
אמינא, hava amina, you know, and maybe that was similar to the
case before when I have rights to invest other people's money. Maybe
I do have a way of making making money and supporting the
family. So here it's really quite interesting. I never said it was
mine, I just said I'll show you the land, I just said
I'll show you the money, show me the money. Okay? And nevertheless,
we interpret it to mean that that means that you will show
her land that you fully own, show money that's fully yours. And
the fact that you have rights to it and can make a
profit off of it is not a fulfillment of the תנאי, tnai,
even though you haven't even said that you'll do that, right? You
haven't even said that it's yours. That is seen so clearly what's
implicit, that if it's not fully yours you did not fulfill the
תנאי. tnai. Did you have a question, Donna? Yes.
And the the money is not yours, I'll show you, it's not
I'm going to give it to you, right? So it's not like
he has to be able to give her this.
Exactly. Exactly.
But we assume the reason he said show was to demonstrate to
her that he has the means of supporting the family. But even
though he never even said mine, and even though he has a
land he's he has access to it and rights to it in
a way to make money off of it, this is what really
is surprising. We read in the word mine and then that has
to be completely satisfied.
Okay, so it's quite interesting here how we define the תנאי. tnai.
Okay, now the גמרא gemara says the following: גבי הקדש תנאי. gabei
hekdesh tnai. Now, what defines whether you have a בית עפר, beit
afar, whether you have this amount of land? You say it's easy,
just get out your, you know, get out your ruler or something
or, you know, go onto Google Maps and measure it. But here
we've got a question, because if somebody sanctifies his field בשעת היובל,
b'shas hayovel, המקדיש שדהו בשעת היובל. hamakdish sadeh b'shas hayovel. Okay, now
the תורה Torah says that when it's the יובל yovel and you
sanctify your field, בית אחוזה, beit achuza, if you your שדה אחוזה,
sedei achuza, if it's time to, if you want to redeem it
from הקדש, hekdesh, rather than paying the market value, you pay a
fixed amount. You pay, you know, for you pay a שקל shekel
for every plot of land that can be בזרע חומר שעורים. b'zera
chomer se'orim. The amount of land that you plant a חומר chomer
of a a certain quantity of barley of barley seed on it.
Okay, so that's the הלכה, halacha, that's in the תורה. Torah. Okay,
נותן בזרע חומר שעורים, nosein b'zera chomer se'orim, for every for every
plot of land the size of the plot that that you would
plant a חומר, chomer, whatever that is, a certain quantity of barley
seed on, חמישים שקל כסף. hamishim shekel kesef. I said a שקל,
shekel, I meant fifty, חמישים שקל כסף. hamishim shekel kesef. That's explicit
in the תורה. Torah. That's the rate of redeeming it from הקדש.
hekdesh. Now, היו נקעים עמוקים עשרה טפחים. hayu nekakim amukim asara tfachim.
Let's say the land has crevices ten handbreadths deep, which is about,
you know, about three feet deep, או סלעים גבוהים עשרה טפחים, o
slaim gevohim asara tfachim, or rocks ten טפחים tfachim tall, אין נמדדים
עמה. ein nimdadim imah. They're not measured with the land. פחות מכאן,
pachus mikan, less than that, נמדדים עמה nimdadim imah are measured with
the land. Now basically, I'll just tell you an interesting little parenthetical
point. What does it mean measured with? Right, you know, well, I
mean, you know, normally you think, what do you mean measured with,
it means measured with. But no, but let's say, right,
here's your plot of land, okay, and here's your rock, okay. So,
רש"י Rashi says what measured it with means is is that not
only would you sort of say, okay, so this is like X
amount of, like, you know, you would just measure like, you know,
the entire the straight width here, but you would actually measure like
this, go up the rock and down the rock and like that.
So that when you were measuring it, if it's measured with, because
it's part of a flat plot of land, you're actually, I mean
if the whole thing obviously was elevated, you'd just measure the top
area. But since you're basically starting here, if this is seen as
part of the land, let's say it was just a mound, right,
would you just go the straight sort of, you know, width, or
would you actually say the, you know, the the plot that's like,
you know, the the that you would travel, or the plot the
area that could be planted? Now the problem is that you can't
really plant on a rock. Okay, well, which we'll get to in
a minute. But anyway, so that's what רש"י Rashi says. Others disagree.
Others say, no, no, no, נמדדים עמה nimdadim imah just means you
just pretend like it's flat and it's not there. But אין נמדדים
עמה ein nimdadim imah
means that if this is a rock that's too tall, or a
crevice that's too deep, then even if this is the right size,
but you have to subtract, you know, cut out that square of
where the crevice is, okay? So that's some more relevant to us
what the
אין נמדדים עמה ein nimdadim imah is and
then that's. too deep, you have to subtract from the total area.
That's אין דנין עמה.
ein danin imah.
Well, here defined by presumably, but here defined by... well you can't
cultivate a rock which is what we're going to get to, but
here defined by 10 טפחים tefachim higher or 10 טפחים tefachim deep.
So it's not the פשט pshat is not necessarily too tall to
cultivate but just it's in a different space. It's not in the
same 10 טפחים tefachim is considered to be the same רשות, reshut,
anything that's too high or that's too deep is its own separate
location and not part of the same plot of land, okay? So
that's what it says, אין דנין עמה. ein danin imah. ודאזינא בה
va-azinan bah but we asked: נהי דבהדי ארעא לא קדש, nehi de-vahadei
ara lo kadesh, fine, it's not sanctified as one unit with that
whole plot of land, but נקדשו באנפי נפשיהו, nikdeshu beanpei nafsheihu, you
still said "I'm sanctifying this land", so even if you consider the
rocks or the crevices different, you sanctified the whole thing. So now
fine, I got two plots of land that's sanctified, the main area
and the crevice. The crevice is a different space that's sanctified. But
either way, you sanctified everything. What difference does it make if you
say it's part of the land or not part of the land,
okay? So the גמרא Gemara says, וכי תימא vechi teima no, here's
why it makes a difference whether you consider them part of the
land or not. כמה דהוה בית כור לא חשיב. kama de-hava beit
kor lo chashiv. Ah, maybe the תורה Torah says you pay a
redemption value for every בית כור, beit kor, okay? That's what זרע
חומר שעורים zera chomer se’orim is, I should have mentioned that, is
the same בית כור beit kor of the משנה, Mishnah, okay? So
right, the משנה Mishnah says you promised to show this woman a
בית כור, beit kor, this is the comparison we're going to make.
The בית כור beit kor is that case in the תורה Torah
of זרע חומר שעורים zera chomer se’orim that you pay 50 שקל
כסף. shekel kesef. So maybe you'd say ah, what if the plot
of land is less than a בית כור? beit kor? Maybe it
doesn't go into the תורה's Torah category of redeeming it for 50
שקל? shekel? So how much would you redeem it for? So actually
רש״י Rashi says well if it doesn't sit into the תורה's Torah
category, then you would redeem it for market value, which might actually
wind up being more money, okay? There's no way of knowing, but
basically the תורה Torah says there's a fixed amount you redeem. For
every בית כור, beit kor, זרע חומר שעורים, zera chomer se’orim, you
pay 50 שקל. shekel. So you sanctified this plot of land. It
was exactly a בית כור. beit kor. But then you had to
subtract the space where there was the crevices, deep crevices and tall
rocks. So what difference does it make? Those crevices and rocks are
sanctified by themselves. Ah, but since you don't have a full בית
כור beit kor that is sanctified as a unit and also the
crevices and rocks are not a בית כור, beit kor, maybe you
go by a different way of redeeming it, not by the 50
שקל, shekel, maybe each thing gets redeemed based on market value. Could
be more expensive. Anyway, that's maybe that's the issue, that would be
the נפקא מינא nafka mina of whether you look at it as
together or not. גמרא Gemara says that's not true. ורמינהי uraminihi I'll
ask you on that. שדה, sadeh, it says when a person is
מקדיש את שדה אחוזתו. makdish et sadeh achuzato. Why does it say
the field? Why doesn't it just say אחוזתו? achuzato? מה תלמוד לומר?
ma talmud lomar? Why does it have that extra word field? לפי
שנאמר זרע חומר שעורים בחמשים שקל כסף, le-fi shene’emar zera chomer se’orim
be-chamishim shekel kasef, 50, you know, this amount of planting a חומר
chomer of barley, this בית כור beit kor for 50 שקל, shekel,
אין לי אלא ששיעורו בענין הזה. ein li ela she-shiuro ba-inyan hazeh.
Maybe it's only if it's that size land? מנין לרבות לתך וחצי
לתך סאה תרקב וחצי תרקב ואפילו רובע? minayin lerabot letech vechatzi letech
se’ah tarkav vechatzi tarkav va-afilu rova? How do you know even much
smaller sizes of land? Each one of those is a smaller area
measurement. Then even there it would be proportional to the 50 שקל.
shekel. So if it would be a size of land that would
be a tenth of a בית כור, beit kor, it would be
five שקל. shekel. How do I know you do a proportional to
this amount? Pro rate, well proportional. תלמוד לומר שדה מכל מקום, talmud
lomar sadeh mikol makom, any type of field. So now we've got
a question, right? What difference does it make if I say the
whole thing is sanctified and it's 50 and it's a בית כור
beit kor and I pay 50 כסף, kesef, or I say no,
no, no, you can't count the rocks and the crevices. So what
you really have is you have one field that's
49... that's you know, .9 of a בית כור beit kor and
you've got this other rock or crevice that's .1 of a בית
כור beit kor and they're sanctified and they're separate units. Who cares
they're separate units? Piece one would be redeemed in a pro-rated basis.
It all winds up to be the same. What difference does it
make if I call it one unit or two units? So let's
see what the גמרא Gemara says. אמר מר עוקבא בר חמא, amar
Mar Ukva bar Chama, הכא בנקיימי דמיא עסקינן. hacha benikaymei de-maya askinan.
Ah, so this is the point about which תוספות Tosafot was hitting
on, which is is it whether are they is it plantable or
not? We're talking about a crevice that is filled with water. Therefore
what? משום דלא בני זריעה נינהו, mishum dela benei zeria ninhu,
that they can't be planted. דיקא נמי דקתני דומיא דסלעים גבוהים, deika
nami de-katani dumya de-sla'im gevohim, like a rock, שמע מינה. shema mina.
Ah, if it can't be planted, here's the story. If it can't
be planted, then you don't have to then clearly, when do I
redeem based on the 50 שקל shekel per בית כור? beit kor?
If it's a שדה, sadeh, if it's a plantable space. But if
I say this rock is excluded, I've got .9 of a בית
כור beit kor plus a .1 בית כור beit kor rock, so
the .9... And gets redeemed based on the normal 50 שקל shekel
rate, but the point one rock or the point one crevice filled
with water does not is not a field, right? It's not plantable.
Does not get redeemed based on that rate, does it? So how
much would it be redeemed for? Whatever the market value would be.
I don't know how much people are paying for rocks or people
are paying for crevices filled with water, but it is not a
field. Okay, and that's why by excluding it, you redeem the remainder
of the field based on the prorated value, and this gets redeemed
not as a field because it's not plantable. One minute. So then
the גמרא Gemara asks the obvious question. So say that even if
it's less than 10 טפחים, tefachim, if it's not plantable, why does
it get why does it get included into the field? So the
גמרא Gemara says, okay, אי הכי אפילו פחות מכאן נמי. ei hachi
afilu pachot mikan nami. If it's less than 10 טפחים, tefachim, also
why is it included in the field? It's not plantable. No, הני
נגני דארעא מיקרו. hani nagnei de'ara mikru. If it's
if the crevice is less than 10 טפחים tefachim deep and it's
filled with water, it's called like a basin of the land, like
a puddle in the land. שדרה דארעא מיקרו. shidra de'ara mikru. It's
called the spine of the land if it's a rock. Meaning, you
don't have to say if it is incorporated into the field, it
doesn't have to be that every square inch of the field is
plantable. Once you look at it as a part, as a feature
of the field, okay, this is a whole field that basically is
plantable. We can call it a field. If it's got certain areas
that are not, those are just topographical features within the field. But
fundamentally, it's still all a field. So if it was not so
deep or not so high, it's a whole field, that's the right
that's the area of בית כור beit kor and you would pay
50 שקל shekel for the whole בית כור. beit kor. Because we
say if it's too high or too deep, it's not just a
piece of the field, it's a separate space. Once it's its separate
space, then you've got a point nine בית כור beit kor which
you redeem prorated, and then you also have a rock or crevice
which isn't a field at all. Okay,
so that's clear, when it's its own space, it's not included in,
and it's not even a field because you look at it in
its own terms. When it's when it's lower, when it's not as
high and not as deep, then it's a feature of the field
and then you look at the entire field as a unit and
you say this is a plantable field when you look at it
as a unit, even though there are certain areas on it that
can't be planted, and you redeem the whole field as a full
בית כור. beit kor. Okay? Yes. Fascinating ways of looking at land,
doesn't this doesn't this come back in בבא בתרא Bava Batra in
real estate? Well, yes, we're actually going to see a case very
sim similar to it in the next. So that's by הקדש. hekdesh.
By הקדש, hekdesh, something is not seen a crevice is not seen
as part of the בית כור beit kor only if it's filled
with water. Okay, but if it's not filled with water, presumably it
would be part of it. Okay, now, that's by a that's by
that. Now, okay, now that's true by הקדש. hekdesh. גבי מכר תנן,
gabei mecher tenan, and as Dov correctly anticipated, in בבא בתרא, Bava
Batra, when it comes to selling something we taught, והאומר לחברו בית
כור עפר אני מוכר לך. veha'omer lechavero beit kor afar ani mocher
lach. You see, that's there again that phrase בית כור עפר. beit
kor afar. I'm going to sell you a בית כור beit kor
of land. והיו שם נקעים עמוקים עשרה טפחים או סלעים גבוהים עשרה
טפחים. vehayu sham neka'im amukim asara tefachim o sela'im gevohim asara tefachim.
If there were deep crevices or tall rocks, אין נמדדים עמה. ein
nimdadim ima. They're not measured with it. So what I would have
to do is I would have to be giving you more flat
land, right? If I sold you this and this was a בית
כור beit kor and this had a big rock, then you would
tell me that's not part of it, you have to give me
a little bit of an extra space over here. If that rock
were lower, I would say yeah, it's all part of the same
land, don't give me a hard time. But if the rock gets
too high or too deep, it's its own space and I have
to give you I promised you a בית כור, beit kor, I
have to make it up with some extra land. Okay? אין נמדדים
עמה. ein nimdadim ima. פחות מכאן הרי אלו נמדדים עמה. pachot mikan
hare ayloo nimdadim ima. ואמר עוקבא בר חמא, ve'amar Ukva bar Chama,
אף על פי שאין מלאים מים. af al pi she'ein mele'im mayim.
In this case, you have to make up the land if the
crevices are too deep even if they're not filled with water. מאי
טעמא? mai ta'ama? Why is it different? אמר פפא לפי שאין אדם
רוצה שיתן את מעותיו בשדה אחת ותראה לו כשניים ושלשה מקומות. amar
Pappa lefi she'ein adam rotze sheyiten et ma'otav besadeh achat veteira'eh lo
kishnayim ushlosha mekomot. Because I don't want to pay money for a
field and basically if there's a deep crevice, okay, I cannot even
if you're telling me it's not filled with water, if I want,
I could plant in the crevice itself. But I don't want to
I just want to do one, you know, make, you know, one
set of furrows, one set of harvesting. I do not want to
have to deal with a separate crevice and deal with that as
a separate space in order to plant and to harvest. It's, you
know, it's not it's not, you know, convenient. I don't get the
economy of sort of scale or whatever, you know. So therefore in
that case, even if it's plantable, because it requires separate attention and
separate effort, I can say that it's not what I was meaning
when I was saying I was buying a square acre. I meant
a square acre that I could sort of tend to and plant
and harvest as a unit. So if that's a deep crevice and
it's a separate even if it's theoretically plantable, if it's only plantable
separately, that doesn't count and you have to make it up for
me. You keep the crevice, you make it up for me whatever
for you know with a separate with a separate piece of land.
Yes.
Why does it not hold for would it be the same reasoning
for the other?
Well, yeah, because by the other here the point is is that
because it's a transaction between two people and it's a sale, I
can say that That clearly was what I was hoping to get
out of my money, whereas in the case of redeeming by הקדש,
Hekdesh, it's more like a formal question of does it fit in
the תורה's Torah definition of a, you know, of a בית כור
Beit Kor and as long as the whole thing is like plantable
or whatever, right, then that's the rate in which it gets redeemed.
It's not a transaction and what I was sort of hoping to
get out of my money. Right? So here it's more like a
meeting of minds where it goes more by their assumptions rather than
by the case of redeeming הקדש Hekdesh where it goes more by
like a formal definition. So that's the basic difference. With now that's
what leads the גמרא Gemara then to ask, the reason we're doing
this setup is the גמרא Gemara says,
הכא מאי. Hacha Mai. In our case where he says I'll show
you a בית כור Beit Kor to this woman, what would be
the story if it had a crevice which was not filled with
water? Which which like model would you go
by? Okay? הכא מאי. Hacha Mai. להקדש מדמינן ליה או למכר מדמינן
ליה. L-Hekdesh midaminan leh o l-Mecher midaminan leh. Do we compare it
to הקדש Hekdesh or to this מכר? Mecher? מסתברא, Mistabra, now based
on what I just said to Jenna you might think we would
go by מכר Mecher because it goes by the meeting of minds,
right, and therefore she could say I thought you meant a בית
כור Beit Kor that was one unit that was easy to harvest,
I was expecting, you know, like that you would be able to
make an easy living off of it, I didn't realize it would
be so difficult, it had all those deep crevices that would require
all that extra effort. But nevertheless we say no, as long as
it's not filled with water it's fine. Why? דאמר לה אנא טרחנא
וזרענא ומייתינא. D-amar lah ana tarchana u-zarna u-maitina. Look, yeah, it's extra
effort, but I'll invest the extra effort, you know, I'll plant the
crevice, no problem. If it's not plantable, clearly that wasn't meant, it
was meant a בית כור Beit Kor that was plantable, but if
it's plantable even if it's deep or whatever and it's an extra
effort I'll do it. Now this is again interesting, right, because this
is the same type of claim that was rejected before. Remember before
when he said it'll be within a certain location and it's not,
he can't say, well, don't worry, I'll make it up, I'll exert
the effort. But that's when his condition wasn't met. Here the question
is what does it define that it is it a בית כור
Beit Kor or not? It's not the condition wasn't met but he
says ah don't let it bother you I'll make it up. Here
it is a בית כור Beit Kor based on one measure, not
based on another measure. Which measure do you apply? So this would
be again a case where you might want to look at like
a certain type of a reasonable expectation assumption context if it's, you
know, if it's reasonable that he could say look it's good enough
it's close enough it is technically a בית כור Beit Kor and
I'll put in the extra effort, right, so again that gets to
that interesting question about how do you use assumptions and context to
interpret what the words mean. But that's different than before when actually
the condition wasn't met and he's saying don't let it bother you
it's okay, you know, I can make it up anyway. Here it
is met based on a particular definition. Jenny had a question about
that?
No, just the first time he's sick during planting time and asks
for a proxy.
Right, exactly.
I'll be sure, yeah, you're a big talker, you'll do the all
effort, yeah, good.
So you're basically assuming the flooded areas do not have any value
for them.
Well not no value but that they're not plantable.
But they are plantable in rice, so oh, rice culture must not
have made it.
All right, that's a good one. Always bringing in those
fascinating facts, Charlie, yes, that's true.
The idea of let the buyer beware come in here? In other
words, shouldn't buyer have looked at the land before? Why is this
coming up?
Yeah, I mean, that's an interesting question.
You know,
it's an interesting question. I mean, I think I'm going to push
that off until we get to בבא בתרא Bava Batra because how
much do we say let the buyer beware and even when you
say let the buyer beware you have to satisfy the conditions of
what you said, right, if it wasn't what you said it was.
So and then the, you know, then there's a question about so
so yeah I mean that's an interesting point. I don't know, I'm
going to have to bracket that. That's a good question. Right about
how much do you sort of say any any what what what
you're saying is let the buyer beware means any ambiguity in what
I said should be interpreted in favor of the seller. Right.
And so why shouldn't the buyer be responsible or how much is
the buyer responsible
to check it out ahead of time? Yeah, it's a good question.
It's a good question. All right. Let's take a look. Next משנה.
Mishna. Okay so that was all these on the condition that and
the last thing we felt we dealt with was a, you know,
a little bit of an interesting digression about what you about what,
you know, how how to define a בית כור Beit Kor but
it really touches on the broader issue
about, you know, how much do you go by the literal meaning
of what was said, how much do you employ context to add
things, how much do you employ context or implicit assumptions etcetera to
define what the definition of something is and so on. Okay now
we get to a classic debate about how to formulate your conditions.
רבי מאיר אומר, Rabbi Meir omer, Rabbi Meir said, כל תנאי שאינו
כתנאי בני גד ובני ראובן. Kol tnai she-eino k-tnai bnei Gad u-vnei
Reuven. This is a big one. Any תנאי tnai that is not
like the conditions that the sons of Gad and Reuven, you know,
משה Moshe made with them, if you do this you'll get the
land and if not you won't get the land, אינו תנאי, eino
tnai, is not a binding condition and therefore it means we throw
out the condition and the sale is good regardless or the
קידושין Kiddushin is. then they will then they will get this land
of עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. וכתיב, ukhtiv, and it is written, ואם
לא יעברו חלוצים, ve'im lo ya'avru chalutzim, but if they do not
go ahead armed in front of their brethren Israel, then they will
then they will get with you in the land of כנען, Kena'an,
but they won't get this land. So he says, why? It wasn't
enough to say if they will. He had to say if they
don't, they won't. So presumably, if you say, you are married to
me if I give you 200 זוז, zuz, and you don't say,
and you're not married to me if I don't, then whether you
give 200 זוז zuz or not, the woman is מקודשת. mekudeshet. If
you do not double the תנאי, t'nai, the תנאי t'nai gets thrown
out. Now actually here, there is for anybody who's ever learned propositional
logic, there is a good reason for this because how much do
people remember this? Okay, if P then Q does not mean if
not P then not Q. That's not true. What it means is
if not Q then not P. Yeah, okay, because if P then
Q, it means like you know you know you know if it's
nice, we're going to go on a
picnic.
Okay, that doesn't mean if it's not nice, we're not going on
a picnic. If it's not nice, we'll have to discuss it. Maybe
we will, maybe we won't, depends if we can you know depends
how not nice it is or whatever. Okay, if it's nice, we're
definitely going on a picnic. What that does mean is if we
didn't go on a picnic, right, then it wasn't then definitely wasn't
nice because you told me if it was nice, we're going to
go on a picnic, so we didn't go. If it's if if
if it's not Q then not P, but it does not mean
that if it's not nice, we're not going on a picnic. If
it's not nice, who knows, maybe yes, maybe no. You're married to
me if I give you 200 זוז. zuz. If I don't give
you 200 זוז, zuz, maybe you're still married to me. Okay, so
therefore that's actually technically true, it's not how most people talk, okay,
but it technically is true that if you say, you know, anybody
who talks that way,
okay, I just have to interrupt to tell you one thing my
my brother did when we were in high school, yeah, which is
there was we were taking a test on the I think it
was like a test of like propositional logic and the you know
and like all the precise you know way you sort of phrase
things. And the the teacher had a the test was it had
this list of like statements and the the answers were the assignments
with the the the instructions were: write true by every statement that's
true and false by every statement that's false. So he wrote true
and false by every single statement because he said, you didn't say
write true and only true, so I said I wrote true and
also I wrote true by every statement that's true and false by
every I also wrote another one by it. Oh, okay,
yeah, that's oh well, like not only was I not smart enough
to think of that, I never would have risked my grade on
something like that. But anyway, okay, so that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir says. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says that if you say if
you say if they do this, they'll get the land, they'll get
עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, doesn't mean if they don't do it, they
won't get עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. So therefore if you didn't make
the second part of the condition, then the non-fulfillment of the condition
does not negate the action. The condition is only binding if you
say both the positive and the negative. Now, okay, that is the
primary thing that he emphasizes. Now that there are other things that
do come up from what we learn from תנאי בני גד ובני
ראובן. t'nai Bnei Gad uBnei Reuven. One another is, רש״י Rashi mentions
two other things although the משנה Mishnah clearly is emphasizing what's called
the תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful, the double. רש״י Rashi also mentions תנאי
קודם למעשה. t'nai kodem lema'aseh. If you do this, you will get
the land of כנען. Kena'an. If I give you 200 זוז, zuz,
you are married to me. If I say the other way, you
are married to me if I give you 200 זוז, zuz, because
I stated the act first, it's therefore even though I sort of
tried afterwards to say, wait, wait, wait, it's dependent on the following
thing, since I gave primacy to the act, you are married to
me. If I give you 200 זוז, zuz, no, then you're married
to me. The תנאי, t'nai, the condition, is not strong enough to
undermine the מעשה ma'aseh if it was only articulated later. Okay, that's
just a technical formulation, but conceptually what he's basically saying is, and
you could sort of see this throughout, the act is so powerful
and the idea that a condition can can uproot it or stop
it from taking effect is a huge חידוש. chiddush. So in order
for it to have that power, it's got to be very, very
clear that the whole act is totally conditional. It's got to be
clear that if it's that that you know the conditions under which
it won't take effect, you can't just imply that in a certain
condition it won't, you know, of the negative you can't imply from
the positive. It has to be stated at the very outset as
being all conditional on the following thing. If you've made the condition
later, you give a little bit too much primacy to the act,
the condition is not strong enough to prevent it. רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir requires like you know all the I mean you could imagine
somebody sort of saying, listen, I want to make it very clear,
only if you do this, I you know I am not going
under no other circumstance will I, only if, right? So that's sort
of the way he thinks. Unless you have you you know you
make it clear both sides, you say it ahead of time, otherwise...
The act is so powerful that it'll take effect regardless. Jacob, you
had a question.
This
just resonates with me in terms of human psychology, like when I'm
at camp and I say to my campers: We're going to do
blank if, you know, by the time I get to the
if.
Right, exactly. So you have to start by saying: Listen, if and
only if, right? Which is sort of what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
is saying, right? Okay, so and the third thing רש"י Rashi says,
which is less as a sort of obvious why that it's necessary
is, what's the third thing? Hold on.
Oh,
yeah, actually, it's the positive before the negative. If you do—I guess
it—yeah, this I don't understand as much. It's like: If I give
you 200 זוז, zuz, you're married to me. If I don't give
you 200 זוז, zuz, you're not married to me, right? If you
say the reverse: If I don't give you 200 זוז, zuz, you're
not, and if I do, you are. Well, I guess it's the
same point. If you end by: if I do, you are, you're
ending by emphasizing that the act will take effect. And again for
him, you know, in order to make the act is so powerful
that in order to prevent it from taking effect, you have to
very clearly, like in all ways, you know, sort of make it
show that it's tentative. So if you start by saying: If you
do this, you're married, and if not, you're not, you end by
saying there are ways in which you're not going to be married
to me. Okay? Whereas if you start by the not and you
end by: and if you do, you are, somehow that would actually
mean that it would take effect regardless. Okay, so those are the
three major things for רבי מאיר: Rabbi Meir: תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful,
and all of these are in תנאי בני גד ובני ראובן. t'nai
b'nei Gad u'v'nei Reuven. Okay? תנאי קודם למעשה t'nai kodem l'ma'aseh and
הן קודם ללאו. hein kodem l'lav. Okay, those are the three things.
So
if,
you know, I give you 200 dollars, you're married,
okay, so that's תנאי t'nai coming before the מעשה. ma'aseh. Okay? And
if I don't,
you're not married, okay, so this is the תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful,
it's being repeated, okay, and this is the הן, hein, if I
do, you're married, this is the הן, hein, the yes coming before
the לאו. lav. Okay? Only when all three of those conditions are
met is it going to be okay. תנאי T'nai
and this is מעשה. ma'aseh. Here's תנאי כפול t'nai kaful because it's
this and this. And this is the הן hein coming before the
לאו. lav. Yes.
But it says תתקדשי לי על מנת שאתן לך מאתיים זוז. titkadshi
li al mnat she'etten lach matayim zuz.
That would be the מעשה קודם לתנאי. ma'aseh kodem l't'nai. That's מעשה
קודם לתנאי. ma'aseh kodem l't'nai. That's correct.
But every single case we've seen is that. Right.
Because these are רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Those aren't רבי מאיר. Rabbi
Meir. And those also aren't תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful, those earlier משניות.
mishnayot. Yes. Now there's an interesting question, do we פוסקן pasken רבי
מאיר? Rabbi Meir? And maybe we only פוסקן pasken רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir in some of these and not in all of these, particularly
תנאי כפול, t'nai kaful, there's a reason to think we פוסקן pasken
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir although it's not in any of the earlier
משניות. mishnayot. Yes.
That's actually my question. It's rare to see a משנה mishna open
up with a statement specifically attributed to
רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Right, because סתם משנה stam mishna is רבי מאיר, Rabbi
Meir, but also,
like we don't usually identify them explicitly.
Right, right, but the previous משניות mishnayot might not be רבי מאיר.
Rabbi Meir. Okay, that's what רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says. רבי
חנינא בן גמליאל אומר: Rabbi Hanina ben Gamliel omer: צריך הדבר לאומרו.
tzarich hadavar l'omro. No,
the repetition here is not to tell you there's a general need
for תנאי כפול. t'nai kaful. If Moshe had not said: And if
you don't go over, you'll get in Canaan, I could have anyway
learned that if they didn't go over, they wouldn't get עבר הירדן.
Ever HaYarden.
So why did Moshe have to repeat it? For the following reason:
שאלמלא כן, she'ilmalei ken, had he not said that, יש במשמע שאפילו
בארץ כנען לא ינחלו. yes bamashma she'afilu b'eretz Canaan lo yinchalu.
If Moshe had said: If you go over, you'll get עבר הירדן,
Ever HaYarden, full stop, what would I have said? And if you
don't go over, you'll get nothing. Okay, you won't get the part
that you were asking for, and you won't also get ארץ כנען
Eretz Canaan because, heck, you didn't even do anything for ארץ כנען
Eretz Canaan or whatever, that wasn't part of the deal, it was
all about this. So therefore, you didn't need a תנאי כפול t'nai
kaful to say you wouldn't get עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. The reason
Moshe repeated himself—he didn't repeat himself—the reason he said the flip side
was to say that if you do go over, if you don't
go over, at least you'll get part of ארץ כנען. Eretz Canaan.
Now some of you might be thinking, why is that fair? That's
a question to ask on the פסוקים. p'sukim. Why are they being
told that if they don't help fight the war, they'll get in
ארץ כנען? Eretz Canaan? I mean, you know, they're sitting back doing
absolutely nothing and they should get part of ארץ כנען? Eretz Canaan?
So actually, תוספות Tosafot says on the next עמוד—that's amud what רש"י
Rashi says—that in the end of the day, Moshe was telling them
if you don't fight, you'll get part of Canaan. Why is that
fair? But that's what I think you ask when you read the
פסוקים. psukim. So תוספות Tosafot says no no no. It says אם
לא יעברו חלוצים לפני אחיכם בני ישראל, im lo ya'avru chalutzim lifnei
acheichem bnei Yisrael, that the basic condition was you'll get עבר הירדן
Ever HaYarden if you go ahead and lead the charge. But if
you don't lead the charge, if you don't go at the head
of the army, you just participate normally, you won't get עבר הירדן,
Ever HaYarden, you'll get a normal part of ארץ כנען. Eretz K'naan.
Okay, so that's an interesting question about how to read פשט pshat
of the פסוקים. psukim. When משה Moshe is saying if you don't
go חלוצים chalutzim you'll get ארץ כנען Eretz K'naan but not עבר
הירדן, Ever HaYarden, is he saying you don't go at all or
is he saying you don't lead the charge? Anyway, רבי חנינא בן
גמליאל Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel is saying is that without repeating it,
they would not have gotten, it would have been clear they didn't
get עבר הירדן. Ever HaYarden. The flip side had to be said
to say that they will still get the land of כנען. K'naan.
Let's take a look at the גמרא. Gemara. The גמרא Gemara is
a little bit confusing here, we'll do our best. Okay, שפיר קאמר
ליה רבי חנינא בן גמליאל לרבי מאיר. shappir ka'amar leh Rabbi Chanina
ben Gamliel l'Rabbi Meir. רבי גמליאל Rabbi Gamliel has a good response
to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, that you needed to tell me that
they would get part of כנען. K'naan. אמר
לך רבי מאיר, Amar lach Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir would
say to you no. אי סלקא דעתך לאו לתנאי כפול הוא דאתא,
ei salka daitach lav letnai kaful hu d'ata, if the repetition was
not to tell you for תנאי כפול tnai kaful to tell you
that you know that you won't get עבר הירדן, Ever HaYarden, it
was only to tell you you would get part of the land
of כנען, K'naan, so לכתוב אם לא יעברו ונאחזו בתוככם. lichtov im
lo ya'avru v'ne'echzu b'tochachem. Just say if you don't pass over, they'll
get with you. And that would have told me they got a
portion in the land of כנען, K'naan, right? Because that's what you're
saying, רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, you need to tell me they'll get
land of כנען. K'naan. So just say ונאחזו בתוככם. v'ne'echzu b'tochachem. בארץ
כנען למה לי? B'Eretz K'naan lama li? Why does it have to
say underscore בארץ כנען? B'Eretz K'naan? שמע מינה לתנאי כפול הוא דאתא.
Shma mina letnai kaful hu d'ata. This is teaching you the תנאי
כפול. tnai kaful. How's it teaching you the תנאי כפול? tnai kaful?
Because what בארץ כנען B'Eretz K'naan means is is that you will
only get in the land of כנען K'naan and not in עבר
הירדן. Ever HaYarden. Meaning, here's what this is going to get a
little confusing. Okay, we'll do our best as they say.
It's so true that the green marker doesn't erase well.
Somebody said this is like a דין din in green markers. Okay,
anyway, so, okay, so
אם יעברו בני גד ובני ראובן, im ya'avru bnei Gad u'vnei Reuven,
what is it? Then it's then what's the end of the פסוק,
pasuk, דוב? Dov? ונאחזו אתכם. v'ne'echzu itchem.
No,
if they are יעברו. ya'avru.
ארץ הגלעד, Eretz
HaGilad, I don't know, something. Okay, anyway, okay, אם יעברו, im ya'avru,
here we'll draw a little map of ישראל. Yisrael. Excuse my lack
of artistry. Okay, so here's כנען K'naan and here's what? ירדן? Yarden?
What did you say?
Very political map. Very political map.
Okay, anyway, well, okay, so אם יעברו im ya'avru they'll get ארץ
הגלעד, Eretz HaGilad, okay?
ונתתם להם את ארץ הגלעד לאחוזה.
unatatem lahem
et Eretz HaGilad l'achuzah.
Okay,
so they'll get ארץ הגלעד. Eretz HaGilad. Now, אם לא יעברו, im
lo ya'avru, now remember, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says okay that without
saying תנאי כפול tnai kaful they would have, they would still have
gotten ארץ הגלעד. Eretz HaGilad. Okay, and רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi
Chanina ben Gamliel says no no no, it had to say it,
not to say they won't get ארץ הגלעד, Eretz HaGilad, that was
implicit. It had to say it to tell them they would get
ארץ כנען, Eretz K'naan, okay? ונאחזו בתוככם. V'ne'echzu b'tochachem.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says if it just said ונאחזו בתוככם
v'ne'echzu b'tochachem and then that tells me that they'll get כנען. K'naan.
Why does it say בארץ כנען? B'Eretz K'naan? What do those extra
words add? Because I already would have known ונאחזו בתוככם v'ne'echzu b'tochachem
they get ארץ כנען. Eretz K'naan. It means that had it not
said those words, then if it had just said אם לא יעברו
ונאחזו בתוככם, im lo ya'avru v'ne'echzu b'tochachem, I of course would have
said the absurd conclusion that they'll still get ארץ הגלעד Eretz HaGilad
and they'll get בתוככם. b'tochachem. Because again, without saying if you don't
have a תנאי כפול, tnai kaful, then the first thing remains true.
Okay, so they're going to get ארץ הגלעד לאחוזה Eretz HaGilad l'achuzah
and if they don't pass over, they'll also get ארץ כנען. Eretz
K'naan. That's what I would have read it. Okay, and so if
you're right, רבי חנינא, Rabbi Chanina, then that implicitly this would have
been rejected and all it would have been with this you wouldn't
have needed these words. Why do you need these words? Because these
words are saying only ארץ כנען Eretz K'naan and not גלעד. Gilad.
Not גלעד. Gilad.
So that shows you that you need to reject the original condition
explicitly. Okay, if you did not need to reject the original condition
explicitly, if that would be implicitly rejected, just say ונאחזו בתוככם, v'ne'echzu
b'tochachem, that would have meant כנען K'naan yes, גלעד Gilad no. The
fact that you needed to underscore only ארץ כנען Eretz K'naan means
that otherwise the original condition would not have been rejected and they
would have been entitled to גלעד Gilad as well and this was
needed to tell me only כנען K'naan not גלעד Gilad to reject
the original condition. Yes.
But
some problem it seems to me with that is בארץ כנען B'Eretz
K'naan isn't... rejection, like it's not phrased as a לא, lo, the
phrase is a different sort of thing.
Yes, that's true, but I mean this is getting to the point
where you're doing extra phrases, you know, and we're saying or teaching
me extra things and it's not explicitly part of the stipulation. You're
right. I mean, you could have said it's as though he's just
saying yes, that's saying no to ארץ הגלעד. Eretz HaGilad. Right. That's
correct, but you know, we're doing our best. Okay. All right. Let's
keep on going. So the גמרא Gemara says like this. רבי חנינא
בן גמליאל Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel would say back to you, no,
אלו לא כתב רחמנא בארץ כנען, ilu lo katav rachmana b'eretz Kna'an,
no, you're wrong. We would have anyway anyway known that גלעד Gilad
is rejected. So if we would have known that גלעד Gilad is
rejected implicitly because that's the nature even of a single תנאי, tnai,
why do you have to say בארץ כנען? b'eretz Kna'an? He would
say, אלו לא כתב רחמנא בארץ כנען הוה אמינא ונאחזו בתוככם בארץ
גלעד, ilu lo katav rachmana b'eretz Kna'an hava amina v'ne'echzu betochechem b'eretz
Gilad, because I would have said בתוככם betochechem didn't mean כנען. Kna'an.
Who says what בתוככם betochechem means? I would have said בתוככם betochechem
meant גלעד. Gilad. Now of course, if it means גלעד, Gilad, then
what's the two sides of the condition? Ah, because here is you
get all of the גלעד Gilad to yourself. But if you're not
יעברו, ya'avro, then you're equal partners in the גלעד, Gilad, בתוככם. betochechem.
So I would not have said that it meant כנען. Kna'an. I
would have said it meant you'll be equal partners in the גלעד,
Gilad, but I would not have said that they get a portion
in כנען. Kna'an. Okay, אבל ארץ כנען כלל לא. aval eretz Kna'an
klal lo. So that's why it had to say ארץ כנען. Eretz
Kna'an. So just the תנאי tnai implicitly means if the תנאי tnai
isn't met, they do not get all of גלעד. Gilad. Okay, but
this could not have just but we have to tell me that
they get כנען. Kna'an. And if you had just said this, it
would have meant a piece of the גלעד. Gilad. So it had
to say בארץ כנען b'eretz Kna'an to tell me that they get
the כנען Kna'an that they don't that they also aren't entitled to
some of כנען. Kna'an. רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
would say back, no, בתוככם כל היכא דאתו לכו משמע. betochechem kol
heicha d'ato lachu mashma. No, no, no. בתוככם betochechem means wherever you
have. So with just this, just this would have meant you get
a portion in כנען Kna'an and in גלעד. Gilad. Okay, בתוככם betochechem
means wherever you might be. So without if if if that's all
this was coming to do, this by itself would have told me
what you what you, you know, רבי חנינא Rabbi Chanina think. בתוככם
betochechem means since בני ישראל Bnei Yisrael would have גלעד Gilad and
כנען, Kna'an, they would have part of גלעד Gilad and כנען. Kna'an.
So why did the סיפא seifa say בארץ כנען? b'eretz Kna'an? Because
בארץ כנען b'eretz Kna'an is limiting and it's telling me not you
get a portion wherever everybody gets, you only get כנען, Kna'an, you
don't get any of גלעד. Gilad. And that's because you need to
explicitly reject the first statement, the first תנאי. tnai. Without rejecting the
first תנאי, tnai, then that's still in effect and they would have
still been entitled to the גלעד. Gilad. Okay. I hope you got
the basic sense of that. We're going to move on. Okay. תניא,
Tanya, we taught in the ברייתא. braita. אמר רבי חנינא בן
גמליאל, amar Rabbi Chanina ben Gamliel, משל למה הדבר דומה, mashal lema
hadavar domeh, when this thing he's trying to demonstrate how you had
to say ונאחזו בתוככם v'ne'echzu betochechem was not meant to reject גלעד
Gilad but to entitle them to a portion of the land of
כנען. Kna'an. Okay. לאדם שהיה מחלק נכסיו לבניו, l'adam shehaya mechallek nechasav
levanav, a guy was distributing on his deathbed his property to his
kids. אמר, amar, פלוני בני יירש שדה פלוני, Ploni beni yerash sadeh
Ploni, Reuven will get such and such a field. ופלוני בני יירש
פלוני, u'Ploni beni yerash Ploni, and Shimon will get such and such
a field. ופלוני בני, u'Ploni beni, and Levi, יתן מאתיים זוז, yiten
matayim zuz, if he gives 200 זוז zuz to I don't know,
to charity, to the estate, ויירש שדה פלוני, v'yerash sadeh Ploni, then
he'll get field number three. ואם לא יתן, v'im lo yiten, now,
if he had not said anything else, if he had just ended
there, you would have thought that what? That if he doesn't give,
right, maybe he's out of an inheritance altogether? So then he says,
no, אם לא יתן יירש עם אחיו בשאר נכסים, im lo yiten
yerash im echav b'shar nechasim, then he'll have a portion with his
other brothers. So, meaning this is his way of illustrating that the
reason משה Moshe said ואם לא יעברו ונאחזו בתוככם v'im lo ya'avro
v'ne'echzu betochechem was not to say
they don't get
גלעד, Gilad, it was to say they do get a portion with
everybody else. They still get a piece of everything else, he gets
part of the land of כנען. Kna'an. Okay, מי גרם לו לירש
עם אחיו, mi garam lo l'yerash im echav, what allowed him to
have a portion with his brothers בשאר נכסים? b'shar nechasim? כפלו גרם
לו, kefelo garam lo, the repetition, the flip side. So the reason
משה Moshe said ואם לא יעברו ונאחזו בתוככם v'im lo ya'avro v'ne'echzu
betochechem was not to say they don't get גלעד, Gilad, it was
to say they do get a piece of כנען. Kna'an. The גמרא
Gemara says, one minute, והלא לא דמיא משל למתניתין, v'hala lo damya
mashal l'matnitin, and it's not similar to our משנה. mishnah. התם תני
יש במשמע שאפילו בארץ כנען לא ינחלו. hatam tani yesh b'mashma she'afilu
b'eretz Kna'an lo yinchalu. In our משנה mishnah it says that if
משה Moshe had not repeated the תנאי, tnai, they wouldn't have had
any part of the land of כנען. Kna'an. אלמא כפלה לארץ גלעד
נמי מהני. alma kefela l'eretz Gilad nami mahani. So that means it
said אפילו בארץ כנען לא ינחלו, afilu b'eretz Kna'an lo yinchalu, means
that when they do, it means that in the end, what would
they have gotten had they not gone and fought? They would have
gotten an equal portion in כנען Kna'an and a portion in גלעד,
Gilad, right? Because they would have gotten both. They wouldn't have got
all of גלעד, Gilad, but they would have gotten a piece of
everything. Okay, והכא תני מי גרם לו לירש עם אחיו בשאר נכסים
כפלו גרם לו. v'hacha tani mi garam lo l'yerash im echav b'shar
nechasim kefelo garam lo. Here the repetition gives him a portion with
the remainder. אלמא כפלה לשאר נכסים הוא דקמהני. alma kefela l'shar nechasim
hu d'kamahani. It's only going to help him for the rest. This
is getting a little bit complicated, but the basic point is what
would I have said... Had I,
had I not had this repetition? Had I not had this repetition,
would I have said that they get nothing? Right? And this repetition
tells me that they get גלעד Gilead and כנען, Canaan, they get
a piece, an equal piece of everything. Okay, that's what the משנה
Mishnah sounds like. אף ארץ כנען, Af eretz Canaan, this repetition told
me they get a little piece of everything. Or would I have
said that without the repetition, they're still going to get a piece
of גלעד, Gilead, but I didn't know that they would get any
part of כנען? Canaan? It's a little confusing. Let's just finish this
point. The גמרא Gemara says like this: לא קשיא, Lo kashya, הא
מקמי דנמליה רבי מאיר ונוחזו, ha mikamei denamlei Rabbi Meir venochazu, הא
לבתר דנמליה רבי מאיר ונוחזו. ha lebatar denamlei Rabbi Meir venochazu. The
difference is the phrase ונוחזו. venochazu. ונוחזו Venochazu establishes that by itself
before ארץ כנען, Eretz Canaan, that they would have had a part
of the גלעד. Gilead. The ארץ כנען Eretz Canaan added the part
that they also would have gotten a part of the כנען. Canaan.
So bottom line is that for רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Hanina
ben Gamaliel he says look, without any of the phrase, I would
have known that they would not have gotten all of the גלעד
Gilead to themselves. I would have started with the assumption that they
get nothing, absolutely nothing, okay, because they weren't promised כנען, Canaan, all
you need is one half of the תנאי, tnai, without that תנאי
tnai they get nothing.
ונוחזו בתוככם Venochazu betochachem would have told me they get an equal
piece of the גלעד. Gilead. That's the first thing it needed to
do, to tell me an equal part of the גלעד. Gilead. Second
thing, ארץ כנען Eretz Canaan told me they get an equal part
of ארץ כנען. Eretz Canaan. But this whole thing is needed to
tell me they do get some part of this. But to say
they don't get all the גלעד Gilead that they were promised, that's
obvious from the get-go. Okay, and רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says no,
if they've not done anything here, even had they not fulfilled their
condition they would have gotten all of the גלעד. Gilead. You needed
it to be repeated to reject the promise of the first part
of the condition. Whereas רבי חנינא בן גמליאל Rabbi Hanina ben Gamaliel
says no, obviously they wouldn't have gotten all the גלעד, Gilead, this
is needed to say they get a piece of this and they
get a piece of that. Okay, so we're done with now parsing
the פסוקים. pesukim. Tomorrow we will continue just working out the idea
of double condition according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir. Okay, so to
be continued tomorrow.